<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI SYSTEM  "http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/dtd/tei_lite.dtd">
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"> 
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Arte de las tres lenguas kakchiquel, quiché y tzutuhil, 
                v.2 Popol vuh; and Escolios a la historia de el origen de los Indios.</title>
                <author>Ximénez, Francisco</author>
                <respStmt>
                <resp>translated to English by</resp>
                <name>Catherine L. Addington</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois, USA</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>An encoded English translation of the prologue to the Escolios, found in Newberry Library's VAULT Ayer MS 1515, volume 2, Escolios Folios 01 to 03, recto and verso. 
                Based on the facsimiles provided by online edition of the Popol Wuj hosted by The Ohio State University Libraries at 
                https://library.osu.edu/projects/popolwujs.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="eng">English</language>
                <language ident="myn">K'iche'</language>
                <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
                <language ident="nah">Nahuatl</language>
                <language ident="spa">Spanish</language>
            </langUsage>
            <creation>
                <date>Spring 2019</date>
                <name>Catherine L. Addington</name>
            </creation>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
        <pb f="1r" n="1" xml:id="pb-trans-1r-1" facs="#zone-pb-1r-1"/>
            <docTitle rend="center">Scholia<anchor n="i" xml:id="note-t-i"/> to the Stories of the Origin of the Indians scholiated by <docAuthor>the Reverend Fray Francisco Ximénez, royally appointed<anchor n="ii" xml:id="note-t-ii"/> missionary priest<anchor n="iii" xml:id="note-t-iii"/> of Santo Tomás Chichicastenango<anchor n="iv" xml:id="note-t-iv"/>,
            &nbsp;of the holy Order of Preachers<anchor n="v" xml:id="note-t-v"/></docAuthor>, for the sake of greater awareness among ministers of the customs of the Indians</docTitle>

            <head>Prologue</head>

			<ab>It is true and well known to all who are familiar with Indians that they are the most irregular in their customs of all the peoples found on the globe; and as such, every day many men of good intellect find themselves mistaken<anchor n="1" xml:id="note-t-1"/> about their customs, for when they seem to have attained an understanding of who the Indians are, they find themselves at the beginning of their knowledge and understanding, such that everything they have acquired with their study and diligence in order to better govern them does not suffice in the cases that present themselves. There have been many who have sought to contribute to the understanding of the Indian in their histories, <hi rend="ital"><language ident="lat">summas</language></hi>, and other writings; but I think that what has happened to them is what will happen to all my writings, which is that though I have sought to bring to light what they are, at the end I think I will not have said anything at all.<anchor n="2" xml:id="note-t-2"/> Doctor Petrus Apianus<anchor n="3" xml:id="note-t-3"/> cosmographer of Emperor Charles V, in demarcating the island of Hispaniola, seeks to make them known to the world, saying that they are a people <hi rend="ital"><language ident="lat">in dando liberalissimi, in accipiendo cupidissimi</language></hi> (<hi rend="ital">generous in giving, avaricious in receiving</hi>), and that they spend all day going around a stick in circles. To some extent this manifests the natural inclination of the Indian, who in giving—I doubt that there be anyone more generous in giving, for who will there be who is not entirely possessed by God that, having but
    <pb f="1v" n="2" xml:id="pb-trans-1v-2" facs="#zone-pb-1v-2"/>
            half a <hi rend="ital"><language ident="spa">real</language></hi><anchor n="4" xml:id="note-t-4"/> with no hope of another, being in a state of extreme necessity, gives away even his own vital nourishment with more generosity than the Indian does? And though he lack for food, he can be seen celebrating festivities and performances with so many expenses [...]<anchor n="5" xml:id="note-t-5"/> and he goes into ever greater debt in order to have these celebrations of baptisms and marriages. Nor is there a more avaricious and wretched people, for when inviting one another to their celebrations, and when one village invites another to its festivities, each host must correspond exactly in number and kind to what he had received as a guest. And should one fail to give just one banana fewer than owed, it is the subject of such passion that for that alone a friendship and relationship of many years can come to an end. It is because of this that what Apianus said is merely one contribution to our understanding of the Indian. So it seems to me that the most correct way of making known who the Indians are and their greater comprehension is what many men of good intellect have said, which is that to define the Indians with an adequate definition is to define them by contradictions. Because they are a people with whom everything is extremes, and opposites, and inverses. In the same way as what Apianus said. And continuing with that I say that they are a people: most strong in working, most lazy in not working, most voracious in eating, most frugal in not eating. Most rich in their goods, and extremely poor. And so on with the rest of their situation, and all this so generally, that one is the same as the other, the rich and the poor, the one who is <hi rend="ital">cacique</hi> or leader just like the <hi rend="ital">mazegual</hi>.<anchor n="6" xml:id="note-t-6"/> They are all the same, each as childish as the other. And so he spoke rightly who called them “children with beards.” And in truth they are like children in everything. As Saint Paul said of himself, of his youth,<anchor n="7" xml:id="note-t-7"/> so are all these childish ways, and as such their malicious acts do not have as much weight as those committed by other men belonging to other peoples, and although some will say, as our Father Noreña<anchor n="8" xml:id="note-t-8"/> says in his letter, that they commit great evils, of which there is no doubt, I will say that just as Our Lord God made up for what the brute lacked in skill with natural instinct for the sake of his preservation, so with these he has made up for what they have lacked for their preservation with instinct, which can be better called knowledge than understanding, because if not it seems to me that they would all already have been finished off by all these who throw them toward destruction and termination, taking advantage of their wretchedness to dare to do what they would not otherwise; I am saying they would neither be so audacious with their superiors nor with their equals. And so with these wretches,<anchor n="9" xml:id="note-t-9"/> others become sages; their ignorance makes others brave; their laziness makes others powerful; those who are otherwise incapable of anything will try to bring them to ruin<anchor n="10" xml:id="note-t-10"/> like one who is defenseless. For there is no black slave who is not audacious with them, and who does not mistreat them.</ab>

        	<ab rend="indent">I understand well that all these stories<anchor n="11" xml:id="note-t-11"/> are children’s tales that make no sense; but although that is the judgment that we must make of them from our position, they should not be so judged with respect to those for whom, in proportion to their own understanding, they are as true as the truths of the Gospel are for us Catholics. Nor is it worth examining the inherent contradictions surrounding them, for with such a dearth of understanding they do not notice this. And here the evil of the infernal beast is made known, how he insinuated lies so tailored to their disposition as to have them even more fooled, and how he wants them not just to find these lies or illusions in these stories but also our Catholic truths revealed by the Holy Spirit in sacred scripture, and how he has and believes our Holy Catholic Faith. It is because of this that these stories should not be paid any attention with respect to the great deal of ground the devil has gained among these people; with these errors
<pb f="2r" n="3" xml:id="pb-trans-2r-3" facs="#zone-pb-2r-3"/>
            that he has sown among them from the time of paganism. I consider these weeds<anchor n="12" xml:id="note-t-12"/> that the devil has sown among them to be as grass in vineyards,<anchor n="13" xml:id="note-t-13"/> that growth which everyone knows is the destruction of vines, and despite knowing this the vineyard owners content themselves with uprooting what they see, not noticing that it continues spreading unseen, and when they least expect it they find they have lost their vineyard; and it is not to be helped, for although they have seen some sprouts come forth, they think them weak, and that they will do no harm, not recognizing the damage in time, and then it becomes irremediable. Just so do I understand it to happen with these Indians and their errors with these weeds that the devil sowed among them in these stories of their origin. Which, upon hearing them every day, and seeing with their own eyes all the sprouts coming forth from their superstitions, most of them make light of the stories. Without noticing the origin and root of where they come from, to seek the remedy in time. Our God is jealous<anchor n="14" xml:id="note-t-14"/> in his honor and worship, and does not permit company in his adorations, and so although it may seem to us a thing of little importance, it has great significance in terms of divine reverence.<anchor n="15" xml:id="note-t-15"/></ab>

            <ab rend="indent">I have become convinced, seeing our Catholic truths cloaked in these mistakes, first, of what our<anchor n="16" xml:id="note-t-16"/> Fray Domingo de Vico says in chapter <num>101</num> of the second part of his <hi rend="ital"><language ident="lat">Theologia Indorum</language></hi><anchor n="17" xml:id="note-t-17"/> that these Indians descend from the ten tribes who were lost from among the Jews,<anchor n="18" xml:id="note-t-18"/> and who did not return to their homeland; and thus they preserved in their traditions all the events that the sacred text relates to us, and the devil went about tangling them up with many errors. And second, if they do not descend from those ten tribes, the devil, being so clever, bringing about the arrival of the Holy Spirit to this area through some conjectures, insinuated to them these lies wrapped in many Catholic truths which the Holy Spirit taught us in Sacred Scripture, so that when the Indians heard what the ministers of God’s word had to teach, and their works, about the incarnation of the Word, Mary Most Holy, and the other saints, they would settle more deeply into their errors, thinking that what was taught to them was the same as what they already were taught by the devil through their own priests. And the effect of this could be observed later, in errors brought about in this recently conquered Kingdom of Guatemala,<anchor n="19" xml:id="note-t-19"/> later embraced by all, that Hunahpu<anchor n="20" xml:id="note-t-20"/> was the God preached to them. And that Hun-Hunahpu <hi rend="ital"><language ident="lat">erat filius Dei</language></hi>.<anchor n="21" xml:id="note-t-21"/> And that Xuchinqueꜩali,<anchor n="22" xml:id="note-t-22"/> who is called Xquic in this language, was Mary Most Holy. And that Vahxaquicat was Saint John the Baptist. And that Huntihax was Saint Paul the Apostle. It all seemed like the nonsense that they had learned from the devil, so it was easy for him to persuade them. And since he wants them to be so incredulous and mistrustful of what the priests tell them, this is why I do not know if they entirely assent to our Catholic truths. Because the Indians are of such a quality that if another Indian like them tells them something, there is nothing more true to them, but if it is said by a priest or a Spaniard to whom they have total aversion, there is no way to get them to agree to what they say, and if they appear to agree, it is more out of fear than for any other reason. In this matter they are most defective, our Indian sons, and they are always of two minds<anchor n="23" xml:id="note-t-23"/> regarding what is told to them; you will see them diligently attending church more on the days that they celebrate than on the days of precept,<anchor n="24" xml:id="note-t-24"/> and it is the case that more so than devotions, they are far more satisfied by gatherings, where they have drums and trumpets and the noise of bells, because they are a most boisterous people, and if there is a <hi rend="ital"><language ident="myn">tun</language></hi><anchor n="25" xml:id="note-t-25"/> or dance in which some nonsense
<pb f="2v" n="4" xml:id="pb-orig-2v-4" facs="#zone-pb-2v-4"/>
            or vestigial lore of theirs from their pagan times is performed, what I say—and I was counseled thus by a learned religious of exemplary conduct who had spent many years administering Indians and died very old, Reverend Father Juan de San José of my holy habit—is that these instruments they use, like the <hi rend="ital"><language ident="myn">tun</language></hi> and the big crate they call <hi rend="ital"><language ident="myn">cohom</language></hi> or <hi rend="ital"><language ident="myn">nimacohom</language></hi>. They have a pact with the devil in these instruments which according to them are funereal, only the devil could be the author of such instruments; and although the priests used to give them certain saints’ stories in their language to be sung to the <hi rend="ital"><language ident="myn">tun</language></hi>, to replace the stories they sang under paganism, nevertheless I understand that they sing this in public where the priest can hear them and then in secret they make sweet memories of their paganism. Based on these things, and many others that have come to my attention, I am attempting to assemble these scholia to their history, noting what is ancient history and citing the foregoing stories. And noting what pertains to our holy Catholic faith for the greater convenience of whoever wishes to take advantage of my work. Cautioning here and holding it to be true that unto this day they maintain the same errors and absurdities, and although it seems to be but a flash of fire, there is much conflagration among them. And though in truth it will seem to many an impossible task to uproot these weeds from the whole, it will be no little service to God to try to uproot it tirelessly, with preaching and constant teaching, since it is merely our responsibility to till, plant, and irrigate this field of the Church with the water of teaching, and it is God’s responsibility to grow these plants.<anchor n="26" xml:id="note-t-26"/> Even to him who does not reap any fruit from his work I guarantee many crowns of glory, such as are enjoyed by the Apostle James, on whose vigil I write this, many crowns of glory even without having been able to convert to the true faith more than seven Spaniards through his great and tireless work in his Apostolic office. For this seed of the holy Gospel is of such superior quality, that even if it all falls upon hard soil, never does the sower want for most abundant fruits from his field, which is true of no other field; if he loses it, he loses all, and he loses more who being the sower of the divine word becomes the sower of a great<anchor n="27" xml:id="note-t-27"/> field indeed. I will briefly note all that I can regarding this history, making known many things about the Indians, not in order to show you their barbarity and brutality, but rather to move you toward compassion for these who are redeemed by the precious blood of Christ our Life,<anchor n="28" xml:id="note-t-28"/> for they are being lost; understanding above all that the principal reasons for not letting these absurdities go, and for the faith having not sat well with them, was because the law of God was planted here alongside so many scandals, deaths, and robberies and such turmoil and tumult, and having received it out of fear of death, as is well observed by His Excellency the Most Reverend<anchor n="29" xml:id="note-t-29"/> Fray Bartolomé de las Casas in his writings and disputes with Doctor Sepúlveda,<anchor n="30" xml:id="note-t-30"/> and the Very Reverend<anchor n="31" xml:id="note-t-31"/> Father Remesal<anchor n="32" xml:id="note-t-32"/> in his history, however much certain modern historians would like to bury this. And after having been so poorly planted, the faith has been watered even worse, for although some zealous ministers have sought to put their shoulders to the wheel, later the faith fades with the death or absence of these ministers who took care to water these plants well; and also because they have no place to learn, even<anchor n="33" xml:id="note-t-33"/> those who know how to read, so that they might spread the faith to the rest, for lack of books about the Catholic
<pb f="3r" n="5" xml:id="pb-trans-3r-5" facs="#zone-pb-3r-5"/>
            faith in their language, other than the two parts of our Fray Domingo de Vico’s theology, and the catechism, which are very rarely found since they remain only in manuscript form, and I know from experience that the Indians who have had the good fortune to read them have derived much benefit for their souls, which if many of the aforementioned books had been printed, all could have enjoyed this benefit; and the misfortune of these poor ones has been such that, having brought so many absurdities before His Majesty, his ministers, and others who are not, no one has spoken of this; I do not doubt his piety and desire for the wellbeing of his subjects, and especially of these who are in his charge like children, and that he will not hesitate to spend what is necessary for this work, so that all may enjoy this benefit. This is all they had to consult, and may they not learn Christian doctrine in the Castilian language, as they have accessed it thus far; I do not hesitate to affirm that he who taught it thusly was some minister who the devil took hold of in order to finish removing from these poor ones what little consciousness they have of our Holy faith because he followed something else. What is more: after this most ingenious<anchor n="34" xml:id="note-t-34"/> work, he managed to get them to know Christian doctrine like parrots without any understanding of what they had learned. I would like him who tried this to tell me what he would have gotten out of it if they had taught it to him in Hebrew or Greek, besides exasperating him in order to cram it into his memory, and after all that he was left <hi rend="ital"><language ident="lat">tan quam tabula rasa</language></hi>.<anchor n="35" xml:id="note-t-35"/> Without knowing what he had learned. May those who handle administration try to learn the language of their jurisdiction; what could be easier than for a capable, learned man who knows his obligation to learn it? For he has nothing else to do outside of administration, and not wanting to relocate<anchor n="36" xml:id="note-t-36"/> all the Indians who hardly have time to make a living, and above all their backwardness, and neither can they entirely dedicate their children to learning, for they are their helping hands and feet from the moment they begin to walk to search for what they need. And not distracting themselves by founding cattle farms and cacao plantations, to the great detriment of the Indians and to the deepening<anchor n="37" xml:id="note-t-37"/> of their poverty, which was justly prohibited by His Majesty in his Laws of the Indies.<anchor n="38" xml:id="note-t-38"/> So with all this they will have time for everything. And they will have it excessively, and doing their duty as they should, and as is defended by His Excellency Montenegro in his <hi rend="ital"><language ident="spa">Parrocho de indios</language></hi>, <anchor n="39" xml:id="note-t-39"/> I do not doubt that they will receive a great reward from his Divine Majesty.<anchor n="40" xml:id="note-t-40"/></ab>

            <ab rend="indent">So shall anyone who makes the effort to look at such nonsense as that which arose under paganism and which some still sustain, or the majority of them do; for seen rightly, our own ancestors made even greater mistakes, and there are still many made today when people are more capable and better taught, and every day we are seeing great shame as people apostatize from the faith, crossing over to Judaism, to the sect of Mohammed, that of Luther, and that of Calvin. And even more commonly the witches,<anchor n="41" xml:id="note-t-41"/> whom the Holy Inquisition continuously punishes, and also daily we see the many abuses and superstitions observed among not just backwards people, but even among more capable and learned people. And this where the Catholic faith is found to be flourishing. But much of all this is found among people so backwards, so little taught, and so young and inexperienced in the faith, which they have known for less than two hundred years. So there still tend to be some who heard from their ancestors the errors that they held under paganism and who heard them tell of the human happiness, which they had in their way, before the onset of the dominion of the Spaniards, for being such backwards people, they do not notice the goodness that has come along with them, of entering into the bosom of Holy Mother Church,<anchor n="42" xml:id="note-t-42"/> but rather exclusively remember the mistreatment that they tend to receive from people with corrupted souls, who by their poor treatment cause great despair among these miserable ones;
<pb f="3v" n="6" xml:id="pb-trans-3v-6" facs="#zone-pb-3v-6"/>
            and so they blaspheme the Holy name of God and the Holy Catholic faith in their adversities and works, and looking at the harmony they tend to have in their republics,<anchor n="43" xml:id="note-t-43"/> I doubt there is a more harmonious people. For among them no debt goes unpaid, nor does any offense go unpunished; I laugh at how the harmony of the bees is praised in their republics, having divided up all common duties and tasks among themselves, helping one another, with such submission to those they have named leaders of their <hi rend="ital"><language ident="nah">calpules</language></hi><anchor n="44" xml:id="note-t-44"/> and factions that you will hardly find an Indian among them who does not obey his <hi rend="ital"><language ident="nah">calpul</language></hi> leader, in what he assigns him, and in such a case everyone conspires against him so that he is punished. I do not doubt that they have many reprehensible customs, but they also have others that are very laudable, that God willing will be found among other peoples. I will write in these scholia all that I can, to make these people known as well as I am able, for those to come, so that they will not be ignorant of their customs. Supposing, as I suppose, that many do not know about them, because of the great secrecy they observe among themselves out of fear of the priest or the Spaniard. And especially about their assemblies which they tend to have among themselves. And moreover if those are idolatrous, the secret they keep is such that there is no hope that even the most idiotic boy would carelessly reveal it, and only by speculation can anything be ascertained.</ab>
            <figure>
            	<graphic url="http://i.imgur.com/pwKbFFg.png" rend="center"/>
            	<figDesc>Watermark. See Carlos M. López, The <hi rend="ital">Popol Wuj</hi> in <hi rend="ital">Ayer MS 1515</hi> Is a Holograph by Father Ximénez," <hi rend="ital">Latin American Indian Literatures Journal</hi>.</figDesc>
            </figure>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>